[Music]
for 25 minutes it is time and let's talk
protein all right here's a brief outline
of what we're gonna cover today I'm not
gonna read the whole thing to you
because you're all very smart but this
is the point in the video where I
convinced you to make sure you watch the
entire thing cause you may be thinking
on protein I don't know and now you see
The Listening like oh definitely because
I want to know about something on there
all right so let's get into it right
away now I love this uh this meme if you
will and much credit to whoever did
little ol old comm or whatever the hell
that is but it's really really funny
right so I have other videos where we're
gonna talk about the post exercise
anabolic window and things like that but
I do like to leave this end just to make
you laugh a little bit because it's
important that we have a conversation
about protein itself now I remember
probably being all the way up through a
doctoral student before anyone ever will
actually no one ever really explained
but I finally figured out what people
mean when they say protein because it's
very confusing and so when we in the
exercise science nutrition strength
training kind of field thing about
protein we tend to think of okay I eat
steak or a whey protein powder or eggs
or whatnot and that goes into my stomach
and then I get muscles right and that's
partially true but it's really confusing
when you start then getting into the
molecular side biochemistry and other
stuff cuz people throw this term protein
protein protein you're just you're just
so confusing what they're talking about
well one things we have to understand is
protein is a bit of a ubiquitous term
there are tons of different proteins in
your body some of them are the proteins
you think about when you think about
your biceps your quads are the muscles
on you but you have to remember or
realize I guess that even things like
your red blood cells are proteins your
hair your fingernails are proteins I
always look at this picture I always
think I wonder how they wipe their stuff
maybe maybe they watch too much of my
why you fart video and I don't know
anyways like everything right and so
there's so much more going on with
proteome when we talk about us so if we
get in discussions about protein
deficiency it's not just about well I
have plenty of muscle I'm fine
sure we have to realize the other
functions of proteins serve in our body
and so here's just a small list and I
think I pulled this honestly straight
off of Wikipedia or something like that
so you can you can do more stuff but I
wanted to just highlight and put you in
context what we're talking about and so
there are really four different
classical protein types I'm not talking
about okaywe casein soy things like that
those are foods these are what I'm
talking about here are molecular biology
types and classifications of proteins
number one is what we call structural
and this is exactly what we're used to
talking about actin myosin if you don't
remember actin is one of the things that
makes up your muscle and so protein does
provide a lot of structure and in fact
because of this and one of the
assignments that we'll do in my class
you'll figure this out on accidents this
is a bit of a hint here but you
basically can't find any living things
that you would eat that don't have some
protein even grass has protein right and
so it's involved in everything because
it's required to have structure if you
find something in biology that is alive
that has structure it probably is made
of proteins in some percentage ER all
right so it gives in shape and in
structure to the cell or even though
we're gonna help there's proteins in the
cell wall there's protein inside of the
cell there's proteins outside of the
cell I mean they're all over the place
you may also not have realized that all
of your enzymes those things those
catalysts that you need to allow
chemical reactions those are also
proteins okay so it takes a bunch of
different proteins to make those up so
in fact if you want to measure how many
enzymes or in your leg or something like
that you are actually just measuring how
much that protein is there or how active
it is depending what you're doing they
can also be receptors so these can be
embedded in the cell walls and these are
then allowing communication in and out
of this cell and you can see the
examples there for steroids and
glutamate and things like that then they
also have other specific functions so
you may not realize your antibodies your
neural peptides your nucleotides all of
these things are different proteins and
so it really is by far the most
fundamental structure in all of biology
now some other ones that are more some
specific examples of some proteins that
you're aware of and then more
the vast majority this is going to be
sports nutrition here so we're gonna get
into the stuff you really have heard of
BCAAs and all that stuff but just
helping again highlight the bigger
picture here so you're not so confused
in the terminology so for classic
examples keratin I'm sure you've heard
of that but that's what makes up your
hair and nails and that's a very famous
protein hemoglobin is what carries
oxygen around your blood cells the
version of it that's in your muscle it's
called myoglobin right so if you
remember that
Myo meaning muscle so if it's in your
blood it's hemoglobin if it's in your
muscle to myoglobin but those are
proteins insulin you've all heard of
insulin right and when you think of
insulin you think of sugar and
carbohydrate but you have to realize
insulin itself is a protein and then of
course pepsin and that's the thing that
aids in digestion of proteins so it's in
some or very versions of it or similar
some things that are similar to it are
in like digestive enzymes for proteins
and things like that so that's a global
idea and concept of in fact there's
about a hundred thousand different types
of proteins in the human body that you
would be related to humans in terms of
sport nutrition and we're physiology or
health for that matter the last little
piece here we have also helped because
that we have to realize it there's a
very strong relationship between protein
and immunity no I'm simply I'm certainly
not saying that if you eat more protein
your immune system gets better we have
to understand our mises right we have to
understand curves if you have enough
eating more does it make it better if
your insufficient though if you are not
having enough protein in your in your
diet then having more protein will
augment the immune system simply because
you've been cutting it short anyways so
inadequate protein can lead to poor
functioning specifically of the t-cells
which you can go back and look at that
up but look up what that means but
that's a problem and again that's
because your immune system your
antibodies etc are all made of protein
so if you have some sort of insult or
attack in your body and you try to
defend that off and you don't have the
available amino acids to make the
proteins to make the antibodies you're
in trouble
so again if you're eating even a
reasonable even slightly low amount of
protein you're just fine you have to get
probably pretty low in the protein scale
for
immune problems to really develop oh
yeah so let's get into the basics and
start off with at the not the smallest
level but a pretty small look you may
remember from middle or high school or
something like that that you're immune
that your proteins are made up of what
are called amino acids and these are the
smallest functional group of approaching
so there's a whole bunch of them I don't
make my class memorize them you can if
you'd like but I don't make them do that
if you take amino acids and put them
together somewhere between two and fifty
amino acids combined together we call
that a peptide alright it doesn't matter
which ones they are if you stick more of
those together we call that a
polypeptides it's like we call it a
polysaccharide in the case of
carbohydrates and these are non branched
non branched chain of peptides if you
take enough of those things to put them
and put them together one or more of
those polypeptides and now you're
usually talking more than 50 amino acids
we call that a protein that's all we're
really talking about when we use that
phrase protein now like I said there are
I don't call it twenty or so amino acids
and it gets a little bit gray there
depending on what's going on and some of
them are classified as we'd say
essential and some are non-essential you
know these first ones here that of
highlighter are the ones that are called
non-essential that doesn't mean they're
not important but you have to consume
them in your food your body can make
them alright so what that means is we
have the nucleotides we have the the
foundation that's required to say build
alanine so if you need alanine for
whatever reason you can bring in spare
parts at your own body can make a buck
them together these remaining nine
though you can't do that um there's also
like six other ones that are what we
call conditionally essential but that's
really not usually an issue for support
performance folks so the essential ones
are this now if you look throughout the
research and we'll get to this a little
bit later but I would I want to make it
clear in multiple parts of this video
essential amino acid intake is what's
really going to drive the boat and
determine things like maximum muscle
growth it's not as much or well it is
total protein but that's really a
surrogate the more specific thing is are
you getting enough essential amino acids
if you do you cross third of the what
we'll call the threshold of growth and
you'll grow plenty if you continue to
consume
say total protein but you're not getting
enough essential amino acids then even
though you're getting enough protein in
your diet not getting the correct ones
that you have to consume so you may be
leaving a little bit of muscle growth on
the table okay now while we're here I
mean I could go on and make a ton of
videos about all the cool things that
these different amino acids will do like
tryptophan most of you are aware of we
know that that thing up regulator can
help you build serotonin and that makes
you sleepy and all that fun stuff but
the one that you've probably heard the
most about is called leucine that's the
bottom corner that brown-ish or
something like that
the reason you've heard of leucine so
much is because we realize it is a very
specific target and on switch if you
will for what's called muscle protein
synthesis muscle growth and so people
got really excited about that because
they realized oh my gosh if I didn't
make sure that I have a bunch of leucine
I'll get the rest of them really
concentrate on that amino acid that will
help me grow muscle I'll tell you a
second what not that worked but that's
the one that you will see constantly in
fact you can buy essential amino acid
supplements you can also buy
specifically leucine supplements and
they have a special name which I'll tell
you in a second okay but while we're
here we hear these terms a lot like high
quality protein low quality protein
protein incomplete incomplete and all
that simply means is a complete protein
or a high quality protein means it
contains all of the essential amino
acids now different foods have the
essential amino acids in different
quantities but technically for us to
call it a high quality or a complete it
has to have all of them in some
reasonable amount now incomplete
proteins are low quality doesn't mean
they're bad for you it doesn't mean
they're processed or anything like that
they just aren't going to hit the
numbers first amino acid now in some
cases you may not care about that and
most of the time in our world of sport
performance it's a pretty big deal so we
often hear I hear folks conflate like
high quality and low quality again with
like processed meat versus non processed
meat that's not what it means
right now those are may be lower quality
foods if you don't argue that
but it's not a low-quality protein if it
hasn't lost any of its essential amino
acids if it had them to begin with so
that's all that term means
okay so branched chain amino acids is
next and now what that specifically
means it's a chemistry term and if you
can look at the image of the organic
chemistry part in the bottom that just
means that at the end part of it is
branched now functionally why you care
about that you don't but what you might
be concerned about is the fact that the
probably the most famous branched chain
amino acid happens to be loosing so
therefore people got ahold of the idea
that I talked about a minute ago said if
we give you a bunch of leucine we just
marketed it as BCAAs for the most part
it's mostly this there's a couple of
other things but it's mostly leucine
therefore they should have a very
specific and direct activation of muscle
growth and they also are low in calories
etc so it should basically be a trigger
to grow turns out it doesn't do much
with a couple of caveats if you're
having a normal amount or a sufficient
amount of total protein in your diet
adding more of this target won't really
do much I think of it as a light switch
if the light is fully on and if not a
dimmer once it's on it's on and so
there's a thing and what we muscle
physiology that we call a leucine
threshold I would strongly encourage you
to read a lot of work by a Canadian
professor and scientist named Stu
Phillips he's done a ton of excellent
work he's good on social media and his
stuff that's out there it's very
accessible as well as another resource
which we'll talk about at the end of the
video where you can have some fantastic
free and open access reading but he's
showing pretty clearly now that once you
cross that leucine threshold any
additional Lucena BCA's really don't do
anything and the problem for the
supplement companies is most people hit
that loose leucine threshold pretty
easily with food and so they don't
appear to have a real advantage
some people claim and there's some very
weak evidence that you may reduce muscle
soreness a little bit with it so you may
not get quite a sore but honestly it's
not it's not particularly impressive
that research so it generally it doesn't
do much what you can show is if you put
it in like cell culture in ridiculous
amounts it helps if you give it to
people who are going through cancer
cachexia or
wasting perhaps in spaceflight or you
know injured and you're in bed for a
month maybe you have some some help
there and first time you may be like to
actually that's super interesting so
great I don't I don't think pcs are
useless but for sport performance
they're not super important could you
make an argument maybe if you're going
really hypo caloric and you're trying to
lose a ton of weight could you then add
the BCAAs in to preserve muscle mass
yeah maybe there's an argument there but
again it's really not that hard to hit
that leucine threshold so you don't
really need to drop a lot of protein
when you're trying to lose weight
anyways so again they don't go into my
useless category but they go into my mmm
they're very far down my list of things
that I'm really concerned about I
basically never recommend them fanatic
really wants them awesome why they don't
have any harm right like there's no it's
just protein so there's no downside to
them unless of course you're liking your
BCAAs because they're also coming in
like a pre-workout and it's jacked full
of a bunch of stimulants and things like
that and then I would say just take the
stimulus if you like to stimulants and
we'll have to have a separate videos on
the pros and cons of that but don't
confuse it because it's simply I love my
BSA is why cuz they taste amazing well
that's a terrible reason to take it
right you don't like the BCA's you just
like the the sucralose another like
watermelon flavor that they're putting
in their pre-workout thing and that's a
crappy reason so the BCS themselves just
don't have a lot of important function
okay about 20% or so of the amino acids
that you're gonna be are BCA's so they
are fairly common in nature but we're
gonna move past PGA's now so remember
that protein has about four calories per
gram but a major caveat here as you've
seen in some of my other videos if
you've already seen the camp fire
analogy I gave with protein
carbohydrates and fat go back and watch
that but remember protein is not really
here to give us energy although it
certainly has it in its primary job is
structure and so we we can metabolize it
for fuel and there are some very
specific exercise physiology things that
we would cover in that realm but for
most part fat protein or fat and
carbohydrate rather or where we get our
fuel for exercise protein is therefore
structured to build hair now hair and
nails right to build antibodies to build
red blood cells to build tissue right so
we don't want to go burning matches for
the sake of energy it's a really poor an
inefficient system and so also along the
lines our amino acids are actually not
stored particularly well in muscle we
are excellent storing fat we are
excellent at storing carbohydrate again
if you think about the function it makes
total sense those are our fuel sources
and we want to be able to have backup
fuel we don't use protein as a backup
fuel in so we have a very difficult time
storing it as I'll show you in a second
yes you can convert some amino acids
into fat but it's again it's a really
bad process so you don't really want to
do it so you can store a little bit of
amino acids in your tissue in the muscle
some very specific ones but for the most
part you really can't now I want you to
think for a second what's the functional
meaning of that in other words given the
fact that you can store carbs well and
you can store fat well but you can't
store protein well what's that mean in
terms of sports nutrition I'm not just
gonna give this to you
there's two or three important things
here that you can think of right well
number one if I can't store protein well
and I'm trying to maximize my
utilization of protein for the sake of
same muscle growth what's that mean
well that probably possibly means I need
to eat protein more frequently and this
is exactly why the bodybuilders did the
old six to eight meals a day
super frequent smaller meals even the
same total amount broken up into smaller
groups consume consume consume consume
to make sure that there are amino acids
available at all times whenever your
body is there to actually it is allowed
to gross the muscles now if you look at
the literature it does appear that total
protein throughout the day is more
important than make specific timing in
most cases
and so that kind of flied back and said
alright maybe it's not a super big deal
to have them all the time but you
probably don't want to have one bolus of
protein a day or rather I'll sit this
way if you probably compared having just
protein once a day or even like once
every two or three days a very low
protein diet maybe like oh I meet once a
week if you're trying to gain mass it's
probably detrimental in fact even if
you're trying to preserve your muscle
mass its rapid probably detrimental is
it a big deal if you have three meals of
protein a day versus six probably not as
long as you're getting the same total
amount of protein so a little bit of
context in that cereal a couple of other
important meanings of this I will get to
them in just a second if you don't have
it figured out a couple other ones on
your own you'll have to wait so when we
do break these proteins down you have
three real end products of it or places
things that can happen number one any of
these damaged proteins in your body so
if you have damaged muscle tissue for
example or you found in a cell floating
around in your sasaki its kind of
damaged it's not functioning it's not
communicating properly with the cell
next to it your body will break it down
and some of those amino acids are then
because remember you build with amino
acids together to make a protein so when
you break a protein down you get a bunch
of amino acids some of those can be
oxidized in the Krebs cycle TCA cycle if
you're more familiar that's the same
pathway that you oxidize carbohydrates
and fat so it can it can be used there
in other words makes a little bit of ATP
energy but not much you can also kind of
recycle the amino acids and use those
for other compounds like your
neurotransmitters hormones albumin
things like that or you can go through a
process called gluconeogenesis where you
convert the amino acids to glucose all
right and then that's very very possible
as well again it's pretty inefficient
but a plausible and possible destination
of the amino acids getting it to fat
it's quite a bit more difficult all
right so I'll give you a couple of
answers here one other I've already
given you one that means of this idea
that protein
samia's is a bit more transient the
other one would be what about overeating
so if you do a carbohydrates
they're very easy to store if you
overeat Pro a fat very easy to store
what about protein though of course if
you are in caloric excess you're going
to storm and gain more weight but you're
probably least and less likely to get
fat by overeating protein then you are
from overeating carbs or fat okay and
that's a really important thing in fact
if you look at the research I would
point point you to dr. Julianne Antonio
stuff and he's shown this just over and
over and over again that even if you put
people way way way way way I mean way up
on protein they don't necessarily gain
weight if you don't go up in fat carbs
and so it is the macronutrient that I
use a lot even when we're trying to go
hypo caloric you know lower in calories
and we need so we can lose weight
because you can keep it really high
people still feel full they recover
reasonably well like damaged ones and
you can still lose weight pretty easily
so it's very helpful that way and now
you understand a little bit about why
the mechanisms are what they are so to
finish this little short version of 25
minute phys up here are some
recommendations in terms of how much
protein to eat now if you want the easy
idiot version just simply say something
like one gram per pound of body weight
or a little bit less if you weigh 150
pounds eat 130 or so grams of protein a
day it's probably close enough now this
chart is nice because it does separate
them off by different categories of
goals and even populations and in fact
the one that I want to draw your
attention to most is the very bottom of
the elderly you can look up what's
called anabolic resistance but it's very
very very clear at this point as you age
you need more and more and more protein
it's really really important that you
don't lose your muscle mass and you
don't assimilate and utilize the protein
you eat as well as you age when you age
so you need to make sure you just eat
more total protein and that's why those
numbers are pretty high in the
recommendations now these are in grams
per kilogram per day so if you get to
2.2 grams per kilogram per day that
would be the same as one gram per pound
and so if you look at the faces a couple
of other interesting things
endurance folks still need really high
amounts of protein because you're
probably breaking down a lot of tissue
again I mentioned the weight restriction
so if you're trying to lose weight you
don't want to just drop protein you're
gonna be really hungry a lot and it's
just not needed to get there if you're
sedentary you could be a little bit
lower I guess if you like but I honestly
don't think anyone should be that low
there's there's no real need there's no
advantage to being there so there's some
real problems like I said if you don't
build up muscle especially in midlife
when you get to 50 60 70 80 you know now
really getting the older life you're
gonna have problems so I wouldn't drop
the protein too much there's no good
evidence in humans that cutting protein
in the midlife range is gonna have any
help on your Aging in fact what we know
as of now in AFER's the opposite it
could have detriment so be very careful
there again in my students I don't make
you memorize these exact numbers it's
close enough in fact if you just put
everyone at 1.5 grams per kilogram body
weight look that covers just about down
where everybody are you're close enough
to within what I call the functional
range anyways where no one you know if
you're programming 185 grams of protein
a day and they actually had underneath
three who cares it's close enough if
they hit a 1 to 98 underneath a 75 it's
really close enough right
another important thing here to notice
is is there are no sex differences and
why note that is well we do see some of
those things with like carbohydrate but
not with protein so there's no we don't
have any indication that women need more
or less protein than men maybe a little
bit but again if you're in this to say
kind of call everybody 1.5 it's probably
close enough for everyone right now what
that also then means that other we think
about it is we typically recommend
somewhere in the neighborhood of 0.4 or
just call it 0.5 grams per kilogram per
serving and so if you're wondering well
how much do I eat per meal and keep you
call it a half a gram per kilogram body
weight and you weigh say a hundred
kilograms would be 220 pounds that's 50
grams of protein or if you want to go
with the actual thing here that'd be 40
grams of protein so a 220 pound guy or
girl
should have about 40 grams of protein
per meal and if you're bigger or smaller
than that scale it up or scale it down
if you have 40 grams per meal and you
eat four meals per day that's 160 grams
for your 220 pound person that's
probably pretty close okay now I again I
think you should do more but that's this
point four grams per kilogram per meal
is what is really helpful especially if
it's high quality protein they hit that
leucine threshold all right these are
complete amino acids you're gonna be
your essential amino acids within that
our complete protein source sorry you
get enough essential amino acids you hit
pollution threshold you'll be just fine
to preserve or gain muscle that you're
looking for but again I want to mention
- there's very little harm of going even
way higher than this and so these are
kind of just like a minimum amounts for
the most part now I want to point you to
a couple of things rate I mentioned this
earlier I said there are some places you
can go and have some free reading the
International Society of Sports
Nutrition has two or three excellent
position stands on protein and this is
one of them if you're not familiar a
position stand means a whole bunch of
scientists and you can see all of them
there come together and say as a group
of scientists what do we believe is true
based on the evidence we're seeing so
it's not one person's opinion or one
Labs or one schools or one lineage it's
a bunch of people that you know ideally
the most the twenty or thirty most
experienced scientists in a topic get
together and put it out there and this
is exactly what this is so it's all
again it's free it's open access it is
very easy to read even with the limited
scientific background so it's not like a
blog post it's not that easy but if
you're like well I kind of have an
undergrad I'm working through my
undergrad or you're I'm a 35 year old
person here and I just follow this stuff
a lot you should have you're fine you'll
be just fine getting through these
articles especially they do an excellent
job of saying here the take-home
messages here's the conclusions the
summaries all that stuff with bullet
points so I strongly encourage you to
check that stuff out and again it is
open access and free you do not have to
have any account to get there okay now
they cover a whole bunch of things in
these articles so I'm not going to do
that
for you they cover things like protein
redistribution now this is an important
idea so for example if you have a bunch
of mass in your shoulders bunch of
muscle and you don't use your shoulders
for a while and you're trying to glow
say grow your glutes and you're doing a
lot of gloop training and you're not
eating enough protein to keep the muscle
here and to grow it here your body will
redistribute it it'll start taking it
from the places you're not using it and
putting it in other places and that
helps explain a lot of confusion with
saying oh I didn't eat protein or I
gained muscle in my hamstrings or my
arms even though I was only eating 50
grams of protein a day but whatever yeah
you're just probably grabbing it from
other places on your body so when we're
saying these numbers what we're not
saying it's impossible to do this if you
don't hit these numbers what we're
saying is these look like what are
optimal as the science stands now if the
science changes later will change your
opinion but as we understand it now if
you want to maintain the muscle you have
and then put more on some specific place
or overall this is what you need okay so
that's a common trick we see at people
who say oh no it's true all you need is
30 grams of protein a day or something
like that look what I did yeah sure they
took the protein from your hamstrings or
calves or whatever else stuff you
weren't using so again they cover more
on this topic of protein redistribution
they cover extensively the different
types of proteins the advantages how
much to take all that stuff are free and
those articles so honestly it's it's a
better place than for me to play the
numbers out here to score that article
that's easy quick to access same thing
with considerations for vegans and
vegetarians proteins discussions on that
should you have casein for bed is it
really that different is it slow-release
is not what's that dude that eating
before bed make you fat spoiler alert it
doesn't and actually can do the quite
the opposite it's a very good idea and
of course the ridiculous idea that high
protein diets are bad for your kidneys
it's not if you have a kidney disease
potentially a problem but I mean
honestly we slam the door on this
question 20 years ago I don't understand
why people still bring it up but if
someone's arguing with you about it or
something and you want the evidence you
want a quick one-stop shop ahead to that
article
now you'll honestly notice that I'm not
even on that so I'm not trying like
I wasn't a part of that thing at all
it's just it's just really really
excellent I used to have a lot of
lecture on all this stuff and I just
threw it all the way and I'm like you
know what it's all right here and it's
so well written just let them do it all
okay so that's it that's our very basics
and foundations of protein if you're new
to my pager order the YouTube stuff here
I got other ones on fat and protein and
a whole bunch of stuff so I would
encourage you to explore around but I do
have one favor to ask
I've been thinking about this typically
I and these videos and just kind of
don't know what to do and I say
something really not funny and kind of
awkward and I just dragged on and I was
like man I need like a catchphrase you
know Mark Bell has his uh making the
world a safer place to lift and strength
is never a weakness and weakness is
never strength and he has he's like
wrestling WWF catchphrases so I need a
catchphrase to end these videos with so
if you've got an idea what I should say
that'd be a real zinger it fits my
personality you gotta let me know if not
in fact you know what if you don't make
some good ideas and suggestions
I'm gonna quit making these videos
that's what my daughter does when she
tries to get what she wants I don't
that's gonna work all right hope you
enjoy peace enema
[Music]